Providence, R.I. Elmwood Christian Church records, 1834-1955.
Congregational Library & Archives
Providence, R.I. Elmwood Christian Church records, 1834-1955.
RG5545
Congregational Library & Archives
0.88 Cubic Feet
(2 boxes)
A Christian Connection church was gathered in 1834 in Providence, Rhode Island, and by 1871 it was known as the Broad Street Christian Church. The Elmwood Congregational Church was first gathered in 1851 and in 1895 it was reformed as the Elmwood Temple Congregational Church in Providence. In 1912, the two churches merged to form the Elmwood Christian Church. The church closed in 1955. This collection includes vital membership records, church records and meeting minutes, legal documents, and programs.
Elmwood Christian Church (Providence, R.I.)
Broad Street Christian Church (Providence, R.I.)
Elmwood Temple Congregational Church (Providence, R.I.)
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Materials were donated to the Congregational Library & Archives by the Rhode Island Conference of the United Church of Christ in April 1984; no accession number.
Historical Note
A Christian Connection church was gathered in 1834 in Providence, Rhode Island. By 1841, the church had a building on Pawtuxet street and was known as the Pawtuxet Street Christian Church. Around 1871, the church moved to a new building on Broad Street and was thereafter known as the Broad Street Christian Church.
The Elmwood Congregational Church, built along Elmwood Avenue, was gathered in 1851 in Cranston, Rhode Island, before moving a short distance North to Providence in 1854. The church reformed as the Elmwood Temple Congregational Church in 1895.
In 1912, the Broad Street Christian Church and the Elmwood Congregational Church merged to form the Elmwood Christian Church. The Broad Street church building was sold and the money was used to build a new church building along Elmwood Avenue. The new building was an English Tudor Revival-style building designed by local architect Gorham Henshaw and construction on the building was completed in 1915. At first, the Elmwood Christian Church was solely a part of the Christian denomination, but by 1934, after the 1931 merger of the Christian and Congregational denominations, the church identified itself as "Congregational-Christian." The church closed between 1954 and 1955. The building has remained a church ever since, first serving as a home to a Presbyterian congregation, then as a home for the Providence Assembly of God, and now as the home for the Impact Center Providence church.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains the records of Elwood Christian Church, In Providence, Rhode Island, and the two churches that merged to form it: The Broad Street Christian Church and the Elwood Temple Congregational Church. The collection includes vital membership records, church records and meeting minutes, legal documents, a pew plan, programs, and clippings.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged into the three series listed below. Materials within each series have been arranged into chronological order by start date.
Series 1: Broad Street Christian Church records, 1834-1882
Series 2: Elmwood Temple Congregational Church records, 1895-1912
Series 3: Elmwood Christian Church records, 1912-1955
Baptismal records.; Church membership.; Church records and registers.; Marriage records.; Pews and pew rights.; Broad Street Christian Church (Providence, R.I.); Elmwood Christian Church (Providence, R.I.); Elmwood Temple Congregational Church (Providence, R.I.); Providence (R.I.) -- Church history.
- Broad Street Christian Church records, 1834 1882; 1834-1882; 1 Volume; 5 Folders
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains records related to the Broad Street Christian Church and includes vital membership records, church records, a pew plan, legal records, and programs.
  - Church records, 1834 1882; 1834-1882 (Box 1, Volume 1)
  - Committee minutes, 1841 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Pew plan, 1841 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Mortgage deed, 1871 1884; 1871-1884 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Pamphlets, programs, and clippings, 1889 1941; 1889-1912, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Membership roll, 1898 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Elmwood Temple Congregational Church records, 1895 1912; 1895-1912; 1 Volume
  This series contains a membership roll for the Elmwood Temple Congregational Church.
  - Membership roll, 1898 1912; 1895-1912 (Box 1, Volume 2)
- Elmwood Christian Church records, 1912 1955; 1912-1955; 2 Volumes; 10 Folders
  This series contains records related to the Elmwood Christian Church. The series contains vital membership records, church administrative records, the church's charter, and programs.
  - Constitution and by-laws, 1912 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Merger documents, 1912 1913; 1912-1913 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Programs, 1913 1919; 1913-1919 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Charter, 1913 1930; 1913, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Member register, 1925 1949; 1925-1949 (Box 1, Volume 3)
  - Pilgrim Fellowship records, 1945 1951; 1945-1951 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Needs survey, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Church records, 1948 1951; 1948-1951 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Member register, 1949 1954; 1949-1954 (Box 2, Volume 1)
  - Programs and clippings, 1949 1955; 1949-1955 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Rhode Island city church survey, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Church records, 1951 1955; 1951-1955 (Box 2, Folder 15)